REICHWEIN PSYCHIATRIC CENTER (MUNICH)
Nie piłeś od tego czasu?
-You haven't had any alcohol since then? -I haven't even had a sip.
CENTRUM PSYCHIATRYCZNE REICHWEINA (MONACHIUM)
Good to hear.
Dobrze to słyszeć.
As long as you don't drink alcohol, you're a man that can start over.
Dopóki nie tykasz alkoholu, możesz zacząć nowe życie.
There's no way I can drink alcohol, what with me meeting you once a week.
Jak miałbym pić, skoro widujemy się co tydzień?
I don't want to be struck by lightning.
- Jeszcze by mnie piorun trzasnął. - Piorun, powiadasz?
I provide respectable counseling.
Oferuję porządną opiekę terapeutyczną.
Well, I don't even have time for drinking.
Nie mam nawet czasu na picie.
This is my first big job since becoming a detective.
To moja pierwsza duża sprawa, odkąd zostałem detektywem.
A big job?
Duża sprawa?
Doctor, what do you think of this man?
Co doktor myśli o tym mężczyźnie?
What do you mean?
To znaczy?
Using your physiognomy skills, Dr. Reichwein,
Doktorze Reichwein, na bazie wiedzy fizjonomicznej,
what kind of man is this?
jaki to jest typ człowieka?
Physiognomy, you say?
Fizjonomika? Serio?
Richard, are you mistaking me for some kind of fortune-teller?
Richardzie, mylisz mnie chyba z jakimś jasnowidzem.
I mean, you're a sensation.
Ale co ci podpowiada instynkt?
They say you can see personalities with just one look at their face.
Ponoć jedno spojrzenie na twarz pozwala ustalić czyjś charakter.
That is the result of meeting clients over many years.
Nie można tego robić bez wieloletnich sesji z pacjentami.
Then use the result of those meetings
Wykorzystaj więc te lata doświadczeń,
to see if this man is a swindler.
żeby stwierdzić, czy to jest kanciarz.
A swindler?
Kanciarz?
Hmph, not this one.
A skąd.
This isn't the face of a swindler.
To nie jest twarz kanciarza.
Even if he tried, he'd be found out right away.
Nawet gdyby próbował, szybko by go wykryto.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Then what about the possibility of suicide?
A samobójca?
I doubt that too.
W to też wątpię.
Suicide is very unlikely with a face like this.
Z taką twarzą nie podejrzewałbym samobójstwa.
With how certain you sound, your physiognomy is strangely convincing.
Mówisz tak autorytatywnie, że twoja fizjonomika brzmi przekonująco.
It's the result of my meetings.
To efekt wieloletnich sesji.
So, why are you asking about this man?
Dlaczego o niego pytasz?
Hans Georg Schuwald…
Hans Georg Schuwald…
Schuwald?
Schuwald?
You know this name, right, Doctor?
Znasz to nazwisko, doktorze?
Yeah, the rich one.
Tak, ten krezus.
He's the Vampire of Bavaria, right?
Wampir z Bawarii, prawda?
Yes.
Tak.
My client is that extremely rich man.
Ten magnat jest moim klientem.
He says that the man in this photo, Edmund Fahren,
Mężczyzna na tym zdjęciu to ponoć Edmund Fahren,
is his own son, of all things.
jego syn. Uwierzysz?
See, he was found out right away, right?
Czyli szybko wyczuł kant, prawda?
No, Schuwald completely believed him.
Nie, Schuwald na wskroś mu uwierzył.
What?
Co?
He deceived him quite skillfully.
Umiejętnie go oszukał.
I went through a lot to ascertain this.
Sprawdzenie tego kosztowało mnie sporo wysiłku.
However, one mystery still remains.
Jednakże wciąż istnieje jedna tajemnica.
How did he know about the existence and background of Schuwald's son
Skąd tyle wiedział o istnieniu i pochodzeniu syna Schuwalda,
enough to convince Schuwald?
że potrafił nabrać staruszka?
Why don't you ask the man himself?
Dlaczego go nie zapytasz?
You see, this man has already committed suicide.
Cóż, ten człowiek popełnił samobójstwo.
What's the big deal, Martin?
O co tyle szumu, Martinie?
Aren't we old friends?
Długo się przyjaźnimy.
At least let me see Edmund Fahren's suicide note.
Przynajmniej pokaż mi list samobójczy Fahrena.
The handwriting analysis is done.
Przeprowadzono analizę pisma.
It is beyond a doubt that he wrote it himself.
Bez wątpienia sam to napisał.
I have no reason to show an outsider like you.
Nie mam powodu, by pokazywać komuś z zewnątrz.
Karl Neuman and Lotte Frank discovered the body.
Karl Neuman i Lotte Frank odkryli ciało.
They know Fahren from his part-time job, right?
Znają Fahrena z jego pracy dorywczej, prawda?
They're just friends.
To tylko przyjaciele.
Just friends, huh?
Tylko przyjaciele?
So, how're you?
A co u ciebie?
Same as always?
Bez zmian?
Yes, even several more of me wouldn't be enough.
Tak. Przydałoby się mnie rozmnożyć.
After taking over for you, I've barely rested at all.
Odkąd przejąłem twoje stanowisko, nie mam chwili spokoju.
Blockhead Martin's finally a bigwig now.
Zakuta pała Martin w końcu jest szychą.
-I won't let you call me that anymore. -What?
- Nie wolno ci już mnie tak przezywać. - Co?
We're no longer boss and subordinate.
Nie jestem już twoim podwładnym.
Come on, Martin…
Martinie…
It seems you don't know how much trouble we went through back then.
Chyba nie masz świadomości, ile nam wtedy narobiłeś kłopotów.
After all that time, we were so close to catching that serial killer,
Tyle wysiłku, seryjny morderca był na wyciągnięcie ręki,
but you were drunk and shot him to death.
a ty się spiłeś i go ukatrupiłeś.
We went through so much cleaning up that mess.
Musieliśmy posprzątać twój bajzel.
Could you please leave now?
Możesz już sobie iść?
We don't have the time to deal with a simple suicide case.
Nie możemy marnować czasu na zwykłe samobójstwo.
I want to visit the crime scene.
Chcę zobaczyć miejsce zbrodni. Zostało należycie zabezpieczone?
Not really, since it's not a crime.
Niezbyt, bo to nie miejsce zbrodni.
I've already given the sign.
Już im wydałem rozkaz.
They're probably moving out the deceased's belongings today.
Pewnie dziś wynoszą własność zmarłego.
Damn.
Szlag.
When did Blockhead Martin become so efficient?
Kiedy zakuta pała Martin stał się taki sprawny?
I got here in time.
Zdążyłem.
But the movers are coming soon to remove everything.
Ekipa od przeprowadzek niebawem wszystko wyniesie.
Oh, it'll only be two or three minutes.
To zajmie tylko dwie, trzy minuty.
So, this is the pipe he hung the rope on.
Czyli sznur zawisł na tej rurze.
He wrote his last words on this desk.
Na tym biurku napisał ostatnie słowa.
Is this the thesis he was writing?
To jego praca magisterska?
The Birth of Tragedy. Process and Reality.
Narodziny tragedii. Proces i rzeczywistość.
The Psychology of Ideologies.
Psychologia światopoglądów.
I see. This bookcase is what a philosophy student would have.
Dobra, biblioteczka studenta filozofii.
This section must be reference materials for his thesis.
Tu pewnie trzyma materiały źródłowe do pracy.
Isn't this The Gallic Wars?
Czyżby Wojny galijskie?
Why is this one unrelated book here?
A ta książka zupełnie tu nie pasuje.
Spanish? No, Latin?
Hiszpański? Nie, łacina?
I can't read it at all.
Nic nie rozumiem.
This book is clean, except for this one underlined part.
Książka jest czysta poza tym podkreślonym fragmentem.
Room 204… Here it is.
Pokój 204… Jesteśmy.
Hey, bring more cardboard boxes.
Przynieś więcej kartonów.
Okay.
Dobra.
We'll start by packing the books into boxes.
Zacznijmy od spakowania książek.
Got it.
Robi się.
Have a good day.
Miłego dnia.
What should we do with this desk?
Co zrobimy z biurkiem?
-That goes over here. -Okay.
- Daj je tam. - Dobra.
Yes?
Słucham?
I want to ask a bit about the room next door.
Mam parę pytań dotyczących sąsiada.
I've shared everything I know.
Już powiedziałem wszystko, co wiem.
No, I'm not with the police. I'm a detective.
Nie jestem policjantem, tylko detektywem.
Whoever you are, you're bothering me.
Kimkolwiek pan jest, jestem zajęty.
My report is due tomorrow,
Mam raport na jutro,
but I haven't been able to concentrate at all with the commotion next door.
ale nie mogę się skupić przez to całe zamieszanie obok.
Okay, then I'll just ask one thing.
Dobrze, zadam tylko jedno pytanie.
Were these two close with Fahren next door?
Czy ta dwójka przyjaźniła się z Fahrenem?
I don't know.
Nie wiem.
I've never seen them in this boarding house.
Nie widziałem ich w tym pensjonacie.
The guy next door didn't seem to have many friends.
Mój sąsiad nie zdawał się mieć wielu przyjaciół.
I see.
Rozumiem.
-We're done now, right? -Oh, wait!
- To wszystko? - Chwila!
Just one more thing.
Ostatnia rzecz.
Geez, what do you want?
Kurde, czego znów?
Can you translate this for me?
Może mi pan to przetłumaczyć?
The underlined part.
To podkreślenie.
Excuse me?
Słucham?
This is no laughing matter.
To nie są żarty.
If I fail my class, you better take responsibility.
Jeśli obleję zajęcia, obwinię pana.
Sorry about this.
Przepraszam.
Let's see…
Zobaczmy…
"I can no longer…"
„Nie mogę już…”
Uh-huh?
Tak?
"…deceive others."
„…oszukiwać innych”.
Right…
No tak…
Wait.
Chwila.
What's that again?
Co?
How would I know?
Skąd mam wiedzieć?
Haven't I done enough?
Nie dość pomogłem?
"I can no longer deceive others."
„Nie mogę już oszukiwać innych”.
I've heard this somewhere before.
Skądś to znam.
Do you like this spot too?
Też lubisz to miejsce?
Hey, you're Johan, right?
Johan, prawda?
Come up.
Chodź tu.
You can see the scenery much better from here.
Stąd widać o wiele lepiej.
Sure.
Jasne.
Thanks.
Dzięki.
Whoa, this is kind of scary.
Rety, trochę tu strasznie.
It's not scary.
Wcale nie.
Hey, get down from there.
Hej, złaź stamtąd.
I said to get down.
Złaź!
I said to get down! It's dangerous!
Masz zejść! To jest niebezpieczne.
Do you come here often?
Często tu przychodzisz?
Yeah, I do.
Tak.
At this hour, people start turning on their lights at home, right?
O tej porze ludzie zapalają światła w domu, prawda?
Families are returning home.
Rodziny wracają do domu.
The smell of dinner comes from out of nowhere.
Zapach kolacji unosi się zewsząd.
I've always longed for that.
Zawsze o tym marzyłem.
Longed for it?
Marzyłeś?
Yeah, ever since I was a kid, I didn't have that sort of thing.
Tak, nie miałem tego od dziecka.
What kind of family did you have?
Jaką miałeś rodzinę?
Oh, sorry.
Wybacz.
Maybe that was insensitive of me to ask.
To było nietaktowne pytanie.
To be honest, I was taken in by foster parents when I was a kid.
Szczerze mówiąc, przygarnęli mnie rodzice zastępczy.
If you don't mind, can I hear it?
Jeśli wolno, opowiesz mi o tym?
What?
Co?
Your story.
Swoją historię.
This was so trivial.
To było banalne.
"I can no longer deceive others."
„Nie mogę już oszukiwać innych”.
It was written in Fahren's suicide note.
To treść listu pożegnalnego Fahrena.
Wait.
Chwila. To nie był list pożegnalny.
All he did was translate this one line in the book and write it down.
Po prostu przetłumaczył i spisał jedną linijkę.
That was my upbringing.
Tak się wychowałem.
It got a bit depressing though.
Trochę to dołujące.
It's strange.
Dziwne.
I feel like I can talk to you about anything.
Czuję, jakbym mógł ci powiedzieć wszystko.
Is the incredibly rich father you mentioned in your story just now
Ten niezwykle bogaty ojciec, o którym wspomniałeś w swojej historii,
Schuwald, by any chance?
to Schuwald?
You're crying
Ty płaczesz
for me?
z mojego powodu?
Hey, we have to do something.
Musimy coś zrobić.
I've been taking care of Schuwald, and he's really worrying me.
Opiekuję się Schuwaldem i bardzo się martwię.
He hasn't been eating properly since Fahren's suicide.
Źle jada od czasu śmierci Fahrena.
At this rate, that guy will die next.
Jak tak dalej pójdzie, on umrze następny.
Karl, how about telling him that you're his real son?
Karlu, może powiesz mu, że jesteś jego prawdziwym synem?
I only wanted to see what kind of person he is.
Chciałem tylko zobaczyć, jakim jest człowiekiem.
If I tell him the truth,
Jeśli powiem mu prawdę,
he'll probably think I'm just a man who is after his money.
pewnie uzna, że zasadzam się na jego pieniądze.
That's the kind of person Schuwald is.
Taki już jest Schuwald. W głowie mu tylko pieniądze.
He won't understand my feelings.
Nie zrozumie moich uczuć.
But you have to do something.
Ale musisz coś zrobić.
Your real father is suffering in the depths of despair.
Twój prawdziwy ojciec pogrążył się w rozpaczy.
I see. So that's how it is.
Rozumiem już wszystko.
What?
Co?
In that case, I have a good idea.
W takim razie mam pomysł.
"I can no longer deceive others."
„Nie mogę już oszukiwać innych”.
The words Fahren left were no suicide note.
Słowa Fahrena nie były listem pożegnalnym.
He had simply translated
Po prostu przetłumaczył
the part underlined in The Gallic Wars, a book in his room written in Latin.
fragment Wojen galijskich, łacińskiej książki, którą miał u siebie.
It seems this wasn't a suicide.
To raczej nie było samobójstwo.
I have no proof.
Nie mam dowodów.
This is just my intuition from my many years in the police.
To tylko intuicja oparta na latach pracy w policji.
Are you listening, Mr. Schuwald?
Słucha mnie pan?
You don't seem too well.
Marnie pan wygląda.
That's enough now.
Wystarczy na ten moment.
What?
Co?
I'm saying that's enough now.
Mówię, że na razie wystarczy.
What are you saying?
Co pan sugeruje?
It's not enough!
To nie wystarczy!
If his death wasn't a suicide,
Jeśli to nie było samobójstwo,
your life may be in danger as well!
pana życie może być zagrożone.
He…
To…
He was my son.
To był mój syn.
Hold on a second.
Chwila moment.
Didn't I report this last time?
Przecież już składałem raport.
His birthplace and upbringing have no connection to you at all.
Nic nie łączy jego miejsca urodzenia i dorastania z panem.
He's an imposter.
To oszust.
It's true that Fahren was a good guy and not the type to swindle others.
To prawda, że dobry był z niego chłopak i raczej nie zwykł kantować,
But he actually tried to trick you.
ale naprawdę chciał pana nabrać.
The master is feeling tired.
Wielmożny pan jest zmęczony.
Please take your leave now.
Proszę odejść.
I refuse to end the investigation here.
Odmawiam takiego zakończenia sprawy.
It's not because this is my first big payment since I changed jobs.
Nie dlatego, że to pierwsza duża robota, odkąd zmieniłem zawód.
I can feel it.
Czuję to.
Some kind of great malice hiding in the background.
Za tą sprawą kryją się niecne czyny.
In life…
W życiu…
In life, there are some things with which you never get a second chance.
W życiu nie zawsze dana jest nam druga szansa.
I wonder if you know that.
Wie pan o tym?
I know that very well.
Aż zanadto.
This investigation isn't over.
To nie koniec śledztwa.
Got it?
Zrozumiano?
Over here!
Tutaj!
The Convention on the Rights of the Child?
Konwencja o prawach dziecka?
Yes.
Tak.
You could call it a shared international pledge
Taka wspólna międzynarodowa obietnica,
to protect the rights of vulnerable children.
żeby chronić prawa bezbronnych dzieci.
That's the topic I'm working with right now.
Właśnie nad tym teraz pracuję.
But I volunteer to take care of children from orphanages
Wolontariacko opiekuję się dziećmi w sierocińcu.
because I enjoy it, rather than for that purpose.
Nie mam w tym celu. Po prostu mnie to uszczęśliwia.
So, let us hear about what you were saying before.
Powiedz jeszcze o tym, o czym wspomniałeś.
Schuwald went bankrupt three times in the past and…
Schuwald już trzy razy zbankrutował…
Yeah.
Tak.
He went missing temporarily each of those three times.
Za każdym razem znikał na jakiś czas.
And when he appeared once more,
Gdy wracał do gry, uporczywie walczył, by odbudować swoją pozycję.
When I was reading books for my part-time job every Friday,
Kiedy czytałem mu książki w piątki,
he told me about this once before.
opowiedział mi o jednym takim zniknięciu.
-Did he tell you where he'd disappear to? -Yeah.
- Powiedział ci, gdzie był? - Tak.
So we just need to take him there.
Musimy go tam zabrać.
Everyone has a place that revitalizes them.
Każdy ma miejsce, które przywraca go do życia.
Just like how you gaze upon the houses from the university rooftop.
Tak jak ty, gdy spoglądasz na domy z dachu uniwersytetu.
What?
Co?
Mr. Kuntz, it seems the sink drain is clogged.
Panie Kuntz, zlew chyba się zatkał.
Could you take a look?
Zajrzałby pan?
It's that sink over there.
Chodzi o tamten zlew.
Lotte, where's the problem?
Lotte, w czym problem?
Hey, open up.
Otwieraj!
Stop messing around.
Nie wydurniaj się.
What is she thinking?
Co ona sobie myśli?
Hey, open up!
Otwierać! Co planujecie zrobić z panem Schuwaldem?
The master has a visual impairment!
Pan niedowidzi!
Open up!
Otwierać!
You're abducting him! Criminals!
Porywacie go! Przestępcy!
Okay, the plan was a total success.
Plan się idealnie powiódł.
Alright, let's go.
Jedź, szybko!
Where are you planning to take me?
Dokąd chcecie mnie zabrać?
Somewhere good.
W dobre miejsce.
I know you're not Margot Langer.
Wiem, że pani nie nazywa się Margot Langer.
But I just want information on the dead Fahren.
Szukam tylko informacji o martwym Fahrenie.
He showed up here, right?
Przyszedł tutaj, prawda?
Which one is Fahren?
Który to Fahren?
"Which"?
Jak to który?
Two parties came to me claiming to be Schuwald's son.
Dwie pary przyszły do mnie, twierdząc, że są synami Schuwalda.
Is it the blond one?
Chodzi o blondyna?
Or the one with the black hair?
Czy o bruneta?
Black hair?
Bruneta?
The one with the black hair came with a girl.
Brunet przyszedł z dziewczyną.
I can't believe he brought a girl with him to a place like this.
Nie do wiary, że zabrał ją do takiego miejsca.
A black-haired boy with a girl?
Brunet z dziewczyną?
Could it be that they were these two?
To mogła być ta dwójka?
Yes, that's them.
Tak.
This young man
Ten młodzieniec
said that he is Schuwald's son?
twierdził, że jest synem Schuwalda?
Is this really the place?
Czy to na pewno tutaj?
There's no mistaking it.
Nie ma wątpliwości.
It's this area.
To tutaj.
Where did you bring me?
Dokąd mnie przywieźliście?
Well, um…
No cóż…
The woods in Obernburg.
Do lasu w Obernburgu.
We wanted to cheer you up.
Chcieliśmy panu poprawić humor.
Let me out.
Wypuśćcie mnie.
Can you see the pond?
Widzicie staw?
Um, yes.
Tak.
Do the fall leaves in the woods look beautiful?
Jesienne liście w lesie wyglądają cudownie?
Yes, very.
Bez wątpienia.
And the wren?
A strzyżyki?
I can't hear the chirps of the wren.
Nie słyszę ćwierkania strzyżyków.
I apologize.
Przepraszam.
This is an industrial district now.
To teraz dzielnica przemysłowa.
Can't you hear it?
Nie słyszycie?
-What? -Huh?
Co?
Listen very closely.
Wsłuchajcie się dobrze.
Their chirps are so beautiful.
Nie słyszycie, jak pięknie ćwierkają.
There are so many apples on the ground near the trees.
Tyle jabłek leży na ziemi pod drzewami.
Give me your hand.
Proszę podać mi rękę.
Please come this way.
Proszę tędy.
What beautiful scenery.
Co za olśniewające krajobrazy.
It's as if the setting sun has made the fall leaves start burning.
Zachodzące słońce sprawia, że jesienne liście zdają się płonąć.
And it's reflecting on the quiet surface of the water, as if it were a mirror.
Odbija się od spokojnej tafli jeziora, niczym od lustra.
You can see it, right?
Widzi pan, prawda?
I can't believe such a view exists.
Niebywałe, że taki widok istnieje.
I see it.
Widzę.
I can see it.
Widzę to.
Wait, what did you say just now?
Chwila, co pani powiedziała?
What?
Co takiego?
You said two parties appeared here.
Mówiła pani o dwóch parach.
The black-haired youth brought a girl with him.
Brunet przyprowadził ze sobą dziewczynę.
Did Fahren come alone?
Czyli Fahren nie przyszedł sam?
Oh, the blond boy came with someone too.
Blondyn też był z kimś.
The Fahren boy you mentioned couldn't speak properly.
Ów wspomniany Fahren nie umiał się dobrze wysławiać.
The young man who called himself his friend gave me specifics.
Ten młodzieniec, jego rzekomy przyjaciel, opowiedział mi szczegóły.
If I had to choose…
Gdybym mogła wybierać…
I would've believed him if he said he was Schuwald's son instead.
uwierzyłabym, że jest synem Schuwalda. Wystarczyłoby tylko jego słowo.
Who is that man?
Kim jest ten człowiek?
Proof
ROZDZIAŁ 27 DOWODY